Guide to the Louis Starr Collection Concerning the Field Notes of William Clark
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Louis Starr collection concerning the field notes of William Clark
1954-1965
WA MSS S-2774
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.8
(13 boxes)
The collection consists of legal records and personal papers that document litigation over William Clark's autograph manuscripts that recorded his impressions (in 1803 and 1804) during a portion of the Lewis and Clark Expedition. The collection is of interest not only for its documentation of the provenance of the Clark manuscripts and litigation concerning their ownership, but also for its relation to the broader legal and historical issues surrounding the distinction between public records and private papers, including replevin and quiet title actions. The files contain court records, correspondence, notes, and files that document the extensive research undertaken by the attorneys engaged in the case (principally Donald F. Hyde), and the contributions of expert witnesses. Also present are records relating to a later case that touched upon similar themes, State of New Mexico v. Kenneth Sender.
Starr, Louis
Associated Materials
Associated material: William Clark, Field notes (WA MSS S-897 (folio)). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis Starr, 1992-1995, and of Abbey K. Starr and Frances Starr Todd, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 13: Restricted Material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Louis Starr
Louis Starr, grandson of General John Henry Hammond, and party to the suit United States Government v. First Trust Company of St. Paul, over the ownership of William Clark's autograph manuscripts that recorded his impressions (in 1803 and1804) during a portion of the Lewis and Clark Expedition. The manuscripts, once in the possession of Civil War General John Henry Hammond, were found in the St. Paul, Minnesota, residence of his daughter, Sophia V. H. Foster, upon her death in 1952. The United States Government asserted that the manuscripts were federal property and sought to acquire them through litigation. At the center of the argument over ownership was the question of whether the manuscripts were official government records, or the personal papers of William Clark. The Minnesota Historical Society also asserted ownership of the manuscripts, claiming that they had been donated by one of the Hammond family heirs (a matter that was complicated by the presence of several heirs who had an interest in General Hammond's and Sophia Foster's estates). The United States Court of Appeals in St. Louis dismissed the federal government's claim in 1958, allowing ownership of the manuscripts to remain with the Hammond family. The Minnesota Historical Society and the family settled out of court in 1958. Frederick W. Beinecke, then the Chairman of the Yale Library Associates, purchased the manuscripts from Hammond family heir Louis Starr, and donated them to the Yale University Library in 1960.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of legal records and personal papers that document litigation over William Clark's autograph manuscripts that recorded his impressions (in 1803 and 1804) during a portion of the Lewis and Clark Expedition. The collection is of interest not only for its documentation of the provenance of the Clark manuscripts and litigation concerning their ownership, but also for its relation to the broader legal and historical issues surrounding the distinction between public records and private papers, including replevin and quiet title actions. The files contain court records, correspondence, notes, and files that document the extensive research undertaken by the attorneys engaged in the case (principally Donald Hyde), and the contributions of expert witnesses. Also present are records relating to a later case that touched upon similar themes, State of New Mexico v. Kenneth Sender.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: June 1992 Acquisition, 1995 Acquisitions, January 2000 Acquisition.
Lawyers -- United States; Government property -- United States; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Personal property -- United States; Public records -- United States; Quiet title actions -- United States; Replevin -- United States; United States -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Lawyers -- United States -- 20th Century; Beinecke, Frederick W.; Clark, William, 1770-1838; Foster, Sophia V. H.; Hammond, John Henry, 1833-1890; Hyde, Donald Frizell, 1909-1966; Sender, Kenneth -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Starr, Louis -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Starr, Louis; Minnesota Historical Society -- Trials, litigation, etc.; First Trust Company of St. Paul -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Yale University. Library; Lewis and Clark Expedition ( 1804-1806)
- June 1992 Acquisition, circa 1955-circa 1956; 3.96; (10 boxes)
  General note
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 157
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  The June 1992 Acquisition consists of records from the law office of McKenzie, Hyde, Willson, French & Poor that relate to the lawsuits over the William Clark manuscripts owned by the Hammond family. The records include research files, transcripts of testimony, memoranda, and correspondence created and accumulated by D. F. Hyde in the course of his work as attorney for members of the Hammond and Starr families. Also included are records relating to the case State of New Mexico v. Kenneth D. Sender, which touched on similar issues as the case involving the Clark manuscripts.
  - Statements on behalf of the Hammonds, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Law memoranda, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government neglect and abandonment, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Metzdorf, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Working material Lewis and Clark, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous photostats, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Lewis and Clark chart, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jefferson-Lewis-Clark correspondence and publication, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research material, photostats, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Appendix III, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Government policy, research material, photostats and printed material, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Research material, photostats and printed material, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Stipulation, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Estate of Sophia W. Hammond, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Record file, United States of America v. Kenneth D. Sender, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Memoranda and briefs, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hammond Appendices I-V, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - State of New Mexico v. Kenneth Sender, 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1958 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Louis Starr Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Donald Hyde Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 25-28)
  - Donald Hyde Correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
  - Donald Hyde Correspondence (Sender file), 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 31-33)
  - Memoranda and briefs, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Unsorted files: notes, memoranda, printed material, and transcripts, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 35-44)
  - Unsorted files: notes, memoranda, printed material, and transcripts, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 45-51)
  - Donald Hyde Correspondence (Sender file), 1961-1964 (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
  - Unsorted papers: notes, memoranda, printed material, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 54-55)
  - Estate of Sophia W. Hammond, 1953-1959 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Notes, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 57-58)
  - Court records, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Memoranda, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Appendices, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1960 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Unsorted files: notes, memoranda, correspondence, 1950s (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - United States v. Sender, memoranda, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 64-65)
- 1995 Acquisitions, circa 1956-1958; 0.21; (1 box)
  The 1995 acquisitions consist of legal briefs and a form letter that outlines the perspective of Louis Starr on the case of the Clark manuscripts.
  - Memorandum of law and legal briefs, typescripts, annotated, circa 1956 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - Form letter from Louis Starr, 1958 July (Box 10, Folder 67-68)
- January 2000 Acquisition, 1954-1965; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 10
  The January 2000 acquisition consists of trial records, articles and press releases, and correspondence relating to the litigation over the Clark manuscripts.
  - Notes and memoranda, 1950s (Box 11, Folder 69-70)
  - Printed material: articles relating to the Lewis and Clark case, 1955-1965 (Box 11, Folder 71)
  - Trial record, First Trust Company, etc. v. Minnesota Historical Society, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 72)
  - Trial record, United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, United States of America v. First Trust Company of Saint Paul and Minnesota Historical Society and Elizabeth F. Bytlacil, Harriet F. Bunn and Roger Sherman Foster, printed version, 1957? (Box 11, Folder 73)
  - Trial transcripts, photocopy, undated (Box 11, Folder 74)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1954, undated (Box 11, Folder 75)
  - Yale University News Bureau, Press Release, 1960 February 14 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - Summary of facts and legal questions ..., by Donald Hyde, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - "The Case of the Clark Papers," by Robert H. Bahmer, draft, 1955 September 30 (Box 12, Folder 78)
  - Memorandum, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 79)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 12, Folder 80)
  - Scrapbook, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 81)
- Restricted material
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 13: Restricted Material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Contracts and financial records from 1992 Acquisition, 1959-1960 (Box 13, Folder 82)
  - Contracts and financial records from 2000 Acquisition (Box 13, Folder 83)